Why do we think
لماذا نعتقد
that stories by men are deemed to be of universal importance,
أن القصص التي يرويها الرجال تعتبر ذات أهمية كبيرة،
and stories by women are thought to be merely about women?
وقصص النساء يعتقد بأنها مجرد حكايات عنهن؟
My grandmother left school when she was 12.
غادرت جدتي المدرسة عندما كانت تبلغ 12 عاما.
She had 14 children.
كان لديها 14 طفلا.
My mother left school when she was 15.
غادرت أمي المدرسة عندما كانت تبلغ 15.
She was a secretary.
كانت تعمل سكرتيرة.
I graduated from university to become a theater director,
تخرجتُ من الجامعة لأعمل مخرجة بالمسرح،
and that progress is entirely to do with the fact that people I'll never meet
و ذاك التطور يتعلق بأن الأشخاص الذين لن ألتقيهم مطلقًا
fought for women to have rights,
ناضلوا من أجل حقوق المرأة،
get the vote, get education, have progress.
للحصول على حق التصويت و التعليم، أحرزوا تقدما.
And I'm determined to do the same, and obviously you are, too.
و أنا عازمةٌ على فعل المثل، و بوضوح أنتم أيضا عليكم ذلك.
Why not?
لم لا؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So I started a festival called WOW, Women of the World, seven years ago,
لذا أقمت احتفالا يسمى (WOW)، اختصارًا لـ(نساء العالم)، منذ سبع سنوات،
and it's now in 20 countries across five continents.
ومنتشر الآن في ربوع عشرين دولة في القارات الخمس.
And one of those countries is Somaliland in Africa.
و إحدى هذه الدول هي صوماليلاند في أفريقيا.
So I traveled there last year,
لذا سافرت هناك العام المنصرم،
and part of the joy I had in going there was going to these caves.
وجزء من المتعة التي حظيت بها هناك كان ذهابي إلى هذه الكهوف.
The Laas Geel caves.
كهوف (لاس جييل).
Now, these caves contain some of the oldest cave paintings in the world.
الآن، هذه الكهوف بها بعض الرسومات الأقدم في العالم كله.
These paintings are thought to be round about 9,000 to 11,000 years old.
يعتقد أن هذه الرسومات تعود لحوالى 9,000 إلى 11,000 عام مضى.
Art:
الفن:
what humanity has done ever since it evolved.
هو ما حققته البشرية منذ تطورت.
It's how we speak about ourselves,
وكيف نتحدث عن أنفسنا،
how we understand our identity,
كيف نفهم هويتنا،
how we look at our surroundings,
كيف ننظر إلى الأمور المحيطة،
who we find out about each other
ماذا نكتشف عن بعضنا البعض
because of the meaning of our lives.
بسبب معنى حياتنا.
That's what art is for.
هذا هو غاية الفن.
So look at this little picture.
لذا دققوا في هذه الصورة الصغيرة.
I think it's a little girl.
أعتقد أنها فتاة صغيرة.
I thought it was a bit like me when I was a little girl.
اعتقدت أنها تشبهني قليلا عندما كنت صغيرة.
And I thought, well, who painted this joyful, youthful figure?
وبعدها فكرت، حسنا ، من رسم هذا الشكل الممتع و النَّضِر؟
And I asked the curator of the caves.
و سألت مدير الكهوف.
I said, "Tell me about the men and women who painted these."
قلت، "حدثني عن الرجال والنساء ممن رسموا تلك الصور."
And he looked at me absolutely askance, and he said,
و نظر إلي مستنكرًا بالطبع و قال،
"Women didn't paint these pictures."
"النساء لا يرسمن هذه الصور."
And I said, "Well, it was 11,000 years ago."
وقلت "حسنًا، كان ذلك منذ 11,000عامًا مضى."
I said, "How do you know?"
قلت "ما أدراك؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And he said, "Women don't do these things.
و رد قائلا "المرأة لا تقوم بهذه الأشياء.
Men made these marks. Women don't."
الرجال من قاموا بها. المرأة لا تفعل."
Now, I wasn't really surprised,
الآن، لم أندهش حقيقةً،
because that's an attitude that I've seen continuously
لأن هذا تصرف أراه باستمرار
all my life as a theater maker.
في حياتي كلها بصفتي مخرجة بالمسرح.
We are told that divine knowledge comes down through the masculine,
أخبرونا أن المعارف السماوية تنزلت من خلال الذكر،
whether it be to the imam, the priest, the rabbi, the holy man.
سواء كان إمام أم قس أم حاخام أم قديس.
Similarly, we're told that creative genius resides in the masculine,
بالمثل، أخبرونا أن العبقرية تسكن في الذكر،
that it is the masculine
إنه الذكر
that will be able to tell us about who we really are,
الذي سيقدر على إخبارنا من نكون حقيقةً،
that the masculine will tell the universal story
أن الذكر هو من سيروي القصة الكاملة
on behalf of all of us,
نيابةً عنا جميعًا،
whereas women artists will really just talk about women's experiences,
بينما الفنانات من النساء سيتكلمن فقط عن خبراتهن،
women's issues only really relevant to women
قضايا المرأة تتعلق بها فحسب
and of passing interest to men --
و تمثل اهتمام عابر للرجل --
and really only some men.
و بالفعل بعض الرجال فقط.
And it's that conviction,
و هذا هو الاقتناع،
that that we are taught,
الذي تعلمناه،
that I think colors so much of whether we're prepared to believe
أنني أعتقد أن هذا يحدد ما تم تهيئة الكثيرين للتصديق
that women's stories really matter.
بأن قصص المرأة لها أهمية بالفعل.
And unless we're prepared to believe that women's stories really matter,
و ما لم نتهيأ للتصديق بأن حكايات المرأة ذات أهمية،
then women's rights don't really matter,
بالتالي لا يكن لحقوق المرأة أهمية،
and then change can't really come.
و عندها لن يحدث تغيير أبدا.
I want to tell you about two examples of stories
أريد أن أحكي لكم عن مثاليْن من القصص
that are thought to be of universal importance:
يُعتقد أن لهما أهمية شاملة:
"E.T." and "Hamlet."
"إي تي" و "هاملت."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I took my two children when they were little --
اصطحبت كلا طفلاي في صغرهم --
Caroline was eight and Robby was five --
كانت (كارولين) في سن الثامنة و (روبي) في الخامسة --
to see "E.T."
لمشاهدة "إي تي"
And it's a fantastic story of this little alien
و يا لها من قصة رائعة عن هذا الكائن الفضائي الصغير
who ends up in an American family
الذي انتهي به الحال مع عائلة أمريكية
with a mum, two brothers and a sister,
تتكون من أم و أخوين و أخت،
but he wants to go home.
لكنه يريد أن يعود لوطنه.
Not only that, but some really bad scientists
ليس ذلك فقط، بل أن بعض العلماء السيئين جدا
want to do some experiments on him,
يريدون إجراء تجارب عليهم،
and they're looking for him.
و يبحثون عنه.
So the children have a plot.
إذن الأطفال لديهم خطة.
They decide they're going to take him back to his spaceship
قرروا أن يعيدوه إلى سفينته الفضائية
as soon as they can,
سريعا قدر الإمكان،
and they plop him in a bicycle basket,
و وضعوه في سلة دراجة هوائية،
and off they ride.
وانطلقوا بعيدا.
But unfortunately, the baddies have found out, and they're catching up
لكن لسوء الحظ، اكتشفهم الأشرار، و لاحقوهم
and they've got sirens and they've got their guns,
متجهزين بصفارات الإنذار و أسلحتهم،
they've got the loud-hailers, it's terribly frightening,
و جهزوا أبواقهم، إنه لشيء مخيف جدا،
and they're closing up on the children,
و يقتربون من الأطفال،
and the children are never going to make it.
ولن يستطيع الأطفال الوصول مطلقا.
And then all of a sudden, magically, the bikes fly up in the air,
وعلى حين غِرّة وبطريقة سحرية، تطير الدراجات في الهواء،
over the clouds,
فوق السحاب،
over the moon,
فوق القمر،
and they're going to save "E.T."
و سينقذون "إي تي"
So I turn to see my children's faces,
لذا التفت لرؤية تعابير أطفالي،
and Robby is enraptured, he's there with them, he's saving E.T.,
كان (روبي) فرحا جدا، لكونه معهم، ينقذ "إي تي،"
he's a happy boy.
إنه فتىً سعيد.
And I turn to Caroline, and she's crying her eyes out.
و رأيت (كارولين) وهي تبكي.
And I said, "What's the matter?"
وقلت، "ما الخطب؟"
And she said, "Why can't I save E.T.? Why can't I come?"
ردت، "لم لا أستطيع إنقاذ "إي تي،" لم لا أستطيع الذهاب؟"
And then all of a sudden I realized:
و فجأة أدركت أن:
they weren't children;
أنهم لم يكونوا أطفالا؛
they were boys --
كانوا صِبْية --
all boys.
جميعهم صبية.
And Caroline, who had invested so much in E.T.,
و (كارولين) التي اهتمت كثيرا بـ"إي تي،"
well, she wasn't invited to save him,
لم تكن مدعوّة لإنقاذه،
and she felt humiliated and spurned.
شعرتْ بالإذلال والرفض.
So I wrote to Steven Spielberg --
لذا كتبت لـ(ستيفن سبيلبرج) --
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
and I said, "I don't know if you understand
و قلت، "لا أعرف إن كنتَ تعي
the psychological importance of what's happened,
الأهمية النفسية لما حدث،
and are you prepared to pay for the therapy bills?"
و هل أنت مستعد لدفع فواتير العلاج؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Twenty years later, I haven't had a word back from him,
بعد عشرين عاما، لم يصلني رد منه،
but I'm still hopeful.
لكن مازال يحدوني الأمل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I thought it was interesting,
لكني اعتقدت أن ذلك كان شيقا،
because if you read reviews of what he intended with E.T.,
لأنكم إذا قرأتم أقوال الصحف لما نواه مع "إي تي،"
he says very specifically,
و يقول تحديدا،
"I wanted the world to understand
"أريد أن يفهم العالم
that we should love and embrace difference."
أننا يجب أن نحب الاختلاف ونقدّره."
But somehow he didn't include the idea of girls' difference
لكن بطريقة ما لم يتطرق إلى فكرة اختلاف الفتيات
in this thinking.
في هذا المعتقَد.
He thought he was writing a story about all humanity.
أعتقدَ بأنه يكتب قصة عن البشرية جمعاء.
Caroline thought he was marginalizing
ظنت (كارولين) أنه يهمّش
half of humanity.
نصف البشرية.
He thought he was writing a story about human goodness;
أعتقد بأنه يكتب قصة عن خير البشر،
she thought he was writing a lad's heroic adventure.
رأت أنه يكتب قصة عن مغامرة بطولية شبابية.
And this is common.
و هذا شائع.
Men feel they have been given the mantle for universal communication,
يشعر الرجال أنهم وُهبوا التواصل العام،
but of course, how could they be?
لكن بالطبع، كيف عساهم أن يكونوا؟
They are writing from male experience through male's eyes.
هم يكتبون عن خبرة ذكر خلال وجهة نظر ذكورية.
We have to have a look at this ourselves.
علينا أن ننظر إلى أنفسنا.
We have to be prepared to go back through all our books and our films,
علينا التأهب للعودة للوراء خلال جميع الكتب والأفلام الخاصة بنا،
all our favorite things,
أمورنا المفضلة،
and say, "Actually, this is written by a male artist --
ونقول، "في الواقع، كتب هذا فنان ذكر --
not an artist.
ليس فنان فقط.
We have to see that so many of these stories
علينا أن نفهم أن العديد من هذه القصص
are written through a male perspective.
كتبت خلال منظور ذكوري.
Which is fine,
وهذا جيد،
but then females need to have 50 percent of the rights
لكن تحتاج الأنثى إلى 50 بالمئة من الحقوق
for the stage, the film, the novel,
في المسرح والأفلام والروايات،
the place of creativity.
و مساحة الإبداع.
Let me talk about "Hamlet."
دعوني أتحدث عن "هاملت."
To be or not to be.
أكون أو لا أكون.
That is the question.
تلك هي المسألة.
But it's not my question.
لكن هذا ليس سؤالي.
My question is: Why was I taught as a young woman
سؤالي هو: لم علموني وأنا يافعة
that this was the quintessential example of human dilemma
أن هذا هو المثال للمعضلة البشرية
and human experience?
و التجربة البشرية؟
It's a marvelous story,
إنها قصة مذهلة،
but actually, it's about a young man fearful that he won't be able to make it
لكن حقيقةً، هي عن شاب يخشى أنه لن يكون قادرا على النجاح
as a powerful figure in a male world
كشخصية قوية في وسط عالم ذكوري
unless he takes revenge for his father's murder.
مالم يثأر لمقتل أبيه.
He talks a great deal to us about suicide being an option,
هو يحكي لنا بنسبة كبيرة عن كون الانتحار خيارا،
but the reality is that the person who actually commits suicide, Ophelia,
لكن الحقيقة هي أن الشخص الذي انتحر فعلا هي (أوفيليا)،
after she's been humiliated and abused by him,
بعد أن قام بإذلالها وإساءة معاملتها،
never gets a chance to talk to the audience about her feelings.
ولم تحظ بفرصة التحدث مع الجمهور عن مشاعرها.
And then when he's finished with Ophelia, he turns on his mum,
و عندما انتهى من (أوفيليا) انتقل إلى أمه،
because basically she has the audacity to fall in love with his uncle
لأنها قد تقع في حب عمّه
and enjoy sex.
وتحظى بالمتعة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It is a great story,
إنها قصة عظيمة،
but it is a story about male conflict, male dilemma, male struggle.
لكنها عن صراع الذكر ومعضلته و معاناته.
But I was told this was the story of human beings,
لكنهم أخبروني أن هذه قصة عن جميع البشر،
despite the fact that it only had two women in it.
برغم حقيقة أنها تشمل امراتين فقط.
And unless I reeducate myself,
و إذا لم أعيد تعليم نفسي،
I am always going to think
سأفكر دائما
that women's stories matter less than men's.
أن القصص عن المرأة أقل أهمية عن قصص الرجل.
A woman could have written "Hamlet,"
كان يمكن أن تكتب امرأة "هاملت"
but she would have written it differently,
لكنها كانت لتكتبها بطريقة مختلفة،
and it wouldn't have had global recognition.
ولم يكن ليُعترف بها عالميًا.
As the writer Margaret Atwood says,
كما قالت الكاتبة (مارجريت أتوود)،
"When a man writes about doing the dishes,
"عندما يكتب رجل عن غسيل الأطباق،
it's realism.
هذا يمثل الواقعية.
When a woman writes about doing it,
عندما تكتب امرأة عن نفس الموضوع،
it's an unfortunate genetic disposition."
يكن هذا ميولًا وراثيًا بائسًا."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, this is not just something that belongs to then.
الآن، هذا ليس فقط شأن يعود لحينه.
I mean, when I was a young girl,
أعني أنني عندما كنت فتاة صغيرة،
wanting desperately to be a theater director,
أردت بشدة أن أصبح مخرجة بالمسرح،
this is what my male lecturer said to me:
هذا ما قاله لي محاضر ذكر:
"Well, there are three women directors in Britain," he said, "Jude."
قال "حسنا، هناك ثلاثة مخرجات في بريطانيا،"
"There's Joan Knight, who's a lesbian, there's Joan Littlewood, who's retired,
"هناك (جوان نايت) السحاقية، و (جوان ليتلوود) المعتزلة،
and there's Buzz Goodbody, who's just killed herself.
و (باز جودبادي) التي قتلت نفسها.
So, which of those three would you like to be?"
لذا من تودين أن تصبحي من هؤلاء الثلاثة؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, leaving aside the disgusting slur on gay women,
الآن، لننحي جانبًا المرأة المضطربة،
the fact is, he wanted to humiliate me.
الحقيقة أنه يريد إذلالي.
He thought it was silly that I wanted to be a director.
ظن أنه من السخيف أني أريد أن أصبح مخرجة.
And I told my friend Marin Alsop, the conductor, and she said,
و أخبرت صديقتي (مارين ألسوب)، قائدة الاوركسترا، التي ردت قائلة،
"Oh yes, well, my music teacher said exactly the same.
"نعم، حسنا، لقد قال لي مدرس الموسيقى نفس الشيء بالضبط.
He said, 'Women don't conduct.'"
قال، "النساء لا تقدن أوركسترا."
But all these years later, we've made our mark.
لكن على مدار كل هذه السنوات بعدها، تمكنا من ترك بصمتنا.
You think, "Well, it'll be different now."
تعتقد، "حسنا، سيكون هذا مختلفا الآن."
I'm afraid it's not different now.
أخشى أنه ليس مختلفا الآن.
The current head of the Paris Conservatoire
الرئيس الحالي للأوركسترا في باريس
said recently, "It takes great physical strength
قال مؤخرا، "هذا يستنفذ قوة بدنية هائلة
to conduct a symphony,
لقيادة سيمفونية،
and women are too weak."
والنساء ضعفاء جدا."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The artist George Baselitz said,
قال الفنان (جورج بازليتز)،
"Well, the fact is women can't paint.
"حسنا، الحقيقة أن المرأة لا تستطيع الرسم.
Well -- they can't paint very well."
حسنا -- لا يمكنهم الرسم جيدا."
The writer V.S. Naipaul said two years ago,
قال الكاتب (في إس نايبول) منذ عامين،
"I can read two paragraphs and know immediately if it's written by a woman,
" أستطيع قراءة فقرتين وأعرف فورا أن من كتبهما امرأة،
and I just stop reading, because it's not worthy of me."
وأتوقف عن القراءة، لأنها مضيعة وقت لي."
Audience: Whoa!
(اندهاش)
And it goes on.
ويستمر هذا.
We have to find a way
وجدنا سبيلًا
of stopping young girls and women
لمنع الفتيات والنساء اليافعات
feeling not only that their story doesn't matter,
من الشعور بأن قصصهن ليس لها أهمية،
but they're not allowed to be the storyteller.
لكن لا يسمح لهن بأن يكن راويات القصة.
Because once you feel that you can't stand in the central space
لأنه بمجرد أن تشعر أنك لا تستطيع أن تقف في الوسط
and speak on behalf of the world,
وتتحدث نيابة عن العالم،
you will feel that you can offer your goods up to a small, select group.
تشعر أنك تستطيع تقديم الخير لمجموعة صغيرة ومختارة.
You will tend to do smaller work on smaller stages,
ستقدم عملا صغيرا على مسرح أصغر،
your economic power will be less,
ستقل قوتك الاقتصادية،
your reach of audiences will be less,
وصولك للجمهور سيقل،
and your credit will be less as an artist.
و الاهتمام بك سيقل كفنان.
And we do finally give artists these incredible, prominent spaces
وبالفعل نمنح الفنانين هذه المساحات الهائلة والمهمة
in the world,
في العالم،
because they are our storytellers.
لأنهم رواة القصة.
Now, why should it matter to you if you're not an artist?
الآن، لمَ يهمك هذا إن لم تكن فنانًا؟
Supposing you're an accountant or an entrepreneur or a medic
بافتراض أنك محاسبًا أو رائد أعمال أو طبيبًا
or a scientist:
أو عالمًا:
Should you care about women artists?
هل عليك الاهتمام بالفنانات؟
Absolutely, you must,
بالطبع، يجب عليك،
because as you can see from the cave paintings,
لأنه كما تفهم من رسومات الكهف،
all civilizations,
جميع الحضارات،
all of humanity
البشرية جمعاء
have relied upon artists to tell the human story,
اعتمدت على الفنانين لتحكي قصة الإنسانية،
and if the human story is finally told by men,
ولو حكاها الرجل في النهاية،
take my word for it,
أؤكد لكم،
it will be about men.
أنها ستكون عن الرجال.
So let's make a change.
لذا لنحدث تغييرًا.
Let's make a change to all our institutions,
لنحدث تغييراً في كافة مؤسساتنا،
and not just in the West.
ليس فقط في الغرب.
Don't forget -- this message of incapability of women
لا تنسوا -- هذه الرسالة عن عدم قدرة المرأة
to hold creative genius
أن تحمل العبقرية الإبداعية
is being told to girls and women in Nigeria, in China, in Russia,
يُحكى لفتيات ونساء في نيجيريا و الصين و روسيا،
in Indonesia.
في إندونسيا.
All over the world, girls and women are being told
في جميع أنحاء العالم، يُخبَر الفتيات والنساء
that they can't finally hold the idea of creative inspiration.
أنهن لا يستطعن حمل فكرة الإلهام الإبداعي.
And I want to ask you:
و أريد أن أطرح عليكم سؤالا:
Do you believe that?
هل تصدقون هذا؟
Do you believe that women can be a creative genius?
هل تعتقدون أن المرأة تستطيع أن تكون عبقرية مبدعة؟
(Applause and cheers)
(تصفيق و هتافات)
Well then, please go forward,
حسنا إذا، من فضلكم تقدموا للأمام،
support women artists,
ادعموا المرأة الفنانة،
buy their work,
ابتاعوا ما تقوم بعمله،
insist that their voices are heard,
أصروا على أن يُسمع صوتها،
find platforms on which their voices will be made.
جدوا منابر حيث يكوَّن رأيها.
And remember this:
و تذكروا هذا:
that in a sense, if we're going to get past this moment
بمعني أننا إذا كنا سنعبر هذه اللحظة الراهنة
of a world where we know that we are unequal,
في عالم نعرف فيه أننا غير متساويين،
it's artists who have to imagine a different world.
أن من عليه أن يتصور عالما مختلفا هم الفنانون.
And I'm calling on all artists, women and men,
و أدعو جميع الفنانين، الرجال والنساء،
to imagine a gender-equal world.
أن يتخيل عالمًا متساويًا في النوع.
Let's paint it. Let's draw it.
دعونا نرسمه و نستوحيه.
Let's write about it. Let's film it.
دعونا لنكتب عنه. ونصوره فيلمًا.
And if we could imagine it,
و إذا استطعنا تخيل ذلك،
then we would have the energy and the stamina
عندها سنمتلك الطاقة وقوة الاحتمال
to work towards it.
اللازمة للعمل على تطور هذا.
When I see this little girl,
عندما أرى هذه الفتاة الصغيرة،
11,000 years ago,
منذ 11,000 عاما مضى،
I want to know that the little girl now
أوقن أن الفتاة الصغيرة الآن
can stand there and think she's entitled to her dreams,
تستطيع النهوض والاعتقاد بأن لها حق في أحلامها،
she's entitled to her destiny
وأن لها حق تحديد المصير
and she's entitled to speak on behalf of the whole world,
وأن لديها الحق في التحدث نيابةً عن العالم كله،
be recognized for it
و أن يُعترف بها في ذلك
and applauded.
و تحصل على الاستحسان.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)